Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin 1730-1776 Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1762 October 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Impatiently awaiting news of Franklin's safe arrival; his friends regret his absence but hope to enjoy his correspondence and share in his discoveries. Mr. Fox extremely obliged to Dr. Franklin for his letter; this draws a similar request from Mr. Hamilton. Congratulates him on his son's promotion; thinks he has a sensible and agreeable wife. Account of certain monies enclosed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1762; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Fitzgerald, ----- and Dr. Charles Morton. London
    Will call on Dr. Franklin, Friday evening, with two ladies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1762?; A.L.S. 1p.; Garrigues, Isaac. London
    Asks for particulars concerning the late Mr.[James] Ralph.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 March 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Mills, John. London
    Begging his acceptance of the first volume of his "Husbandry."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 March 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Whitehurst, John. Derby
    Congratulates him on the appointment of his son to the Governorship of New Jersey. The bearer, Mr. Tunnicliff, is a neighbor of his and a farmer; he desires to purchase two or three thousand acres in America and bring over his family; hopes Mr. Franklin will give him any assistance or advice in his power. Parliament in possession of Mr. Harrison's improvement for measuring equal time at sea; thinks he will receive a handsome reward; the King has ordered this improvement to be made known to all foreign ministers. The King's policy all for the general good and benefit of his subjects. Concerning a "General Theory of the Earth," which he will send him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 April 4; A.L.S. 4p.; Jackson, Richard
    Glad to hear of his safe arrival. Has been chosen to Parliament for Weymouth. Expects to complete his work during the summer. The Speaker frequently inquires after Franklin. Can get no satisfactory information about Mr. Barker or his family; if the heir was in the East India service, can easily procure intelligence of him. Not surprised at the joy universally expressed on Mr. Franklin's arrival in Philadelphia. His letter, containing an account of Madeira, most welcome, he being one of the committee to inquire into its state. Concerning the Act of Assembly received from Mr. Moore.—Question of certain monies allowed Pennsylvania by the Treasury for her defence in 1760 and 1761.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 249).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 April 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Expressing his own and his family's great satisfaction at the news of Franklin's safe arrival.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 May ?; A.L. 2p.; Pringle, Sir John. London
    Reasons why Franklin should return to England. Put into Lord Bute's hands Franklin's proposals as to the preservation of gun-powder, as well as the best means for securing the health of the garrison at Senegal. Shells for Lady Bute. Meetings at his house Sunday evenings. Will send Franklin's account of the paper currency to Lord Shelburne. Dr. Watson's cure of tetanus by electricity.
    (Mutilated.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 June 8; A.L.S. 5p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Sends box by Capt. Friend in the Carolina; in it are books and catalogues for The Library Co., some for J. Bartram and the History of Florida for Franklin. He and Franklin both fortunate in their family connections. Encloses receipt for box of books and one for box of seeds. P. S. From a New York newspaper, see a new colony called New Wales is to be settled on the Ohio; asks him to forward any work relating to this expedition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Armbruster, Anthony. Philadelphia
    Urged by the greatest necessity, or else would not trouble him. Begs Mr. Franklin to send orders to procure him that sum he gave him hopes of, before commencing his journey; his distress very great and if Mr. F. does not rescue him, he will be a great sufferer in his business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 June 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Acknowledging letter, with inclosure to be forwarded to Mr. Hamilton. Mentions box of books again, its contents, etc. Mr. Edwards has published 7th volume of 'Birds and Animals, etc.'; if The Library Co. want to complete their set, let them send in time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 July 5; A.L.S. 4p.; Small, Alexander. London
    Sending him six pounds of burnet seeds and explaining its manifold advantages. Promises him the seeds of an uncommonly good cabbage, which grows in Anjou. Description of the new hemp machine. (Final part missing.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 August 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Entertainment given to Pennsylvania's new Governor [John Penn]; to judge by appearance, he lacks striking abilities, he''ll be the easier governed by his uncle; Proprietor Thomas was there and anxious to Know if Mr. Franklin was coming over to solicit a revival of Dr. Coxe's grant for lands on the Mississippi. Loss of Lord Egremont, hopes they may be as happy in the new appointment. Concerned at the new rupture with the Indians, reasons for it. Mr. Canton thinks he is forgotten. Mr. clark, chaplain to the Earl of Bristol, has published a modern history of Spain. Their friend Hamilton sends thanks for instructions and hopes Franklin will be tempted over soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 September 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Engs, Samuel. London
    Recalls meeting Mr. Franklin at the house of his worthy partner, Mr. Collins, of Rhode Island. Larely arrived from England, but finds climate in Virginia so disagreeable, has decided to go to Philadelphia. Compliments Franklin on his discoveries, experiments and signal services. Having occasion for a trifle of cash, took the liberty to draw on Mr. Franklin for a small amount for travelling expenses to Philadelphia; will remit the money as soon as he arrives in that city.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 September 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Collinson, Peter. London
    Acknowledging his letters from Boston. The enclosed were drawn up at the breaking out of the Cherokee War; a few hints drawn from them might have prevented these cruel recent depredations. News just arrived of their defeat, much concern felt.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 September 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowdoin, James. Roxbury
    Thanking him for his communication of the 19th inst. Quotes a request [in Latin] by Father Beccaria. Congratulates him upon the honors conferred on him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 October 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Griffith. London
    Though Mr. Cumming's letter will inform him of the motive, which induced the friends of the bearer to send him to Philadelphia, yet, as the father of the boy, desired to state his reasons for the step. The lad has been carefully brought up; has been an apprentice for two years, but had too much liberty to go out after the business of the day was over; afraid of his being led into irregularities and extravagances, so, by Mr. Cumming's advice, decided to send him abroad; hopes Mr. Franklin will be so good as to accept him for the remainder of his time; sets forth his attainments; asks that he may be kept closely at work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 October 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Cumming, Thomas. London
    Sends this letter by Capt. Stout. Already greatly in Mr. Franklin's debt, but intends to contract a fresh one; Mr. Griffith Jones, a printer in fleet St., has already written about this matter [I, 81]; advised him to send his son abroad; thought first naturally of Franklin; why he thinks it wiser for him to pay for the boy's passage; hopes the lad will be under the supervision of David Hall; trusts he will make a man like his father. Lord Shelburne's interest in Franklin; on his being appointed Lord of 'I'rade, desired any information Franklin could impart, relative to the public good of his Province; since then a turbulent routish faction occasioned his resignation; he is still the King's favorite and must always have interest everywhere; advises Franklin to write to him and to ignore his resignation. Messages to his wife, son and daughter,— is the last-named married?
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 November 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Sargent, J. London
    Has not had a line from him since his letter of Aug. 8th. His son brought home ill from Eton, but all that is happily over. Lord Egmont's preferment and Lord Hyde's appointment in his place; will carry out his wishes with the latter if possible. Party feeling running high. The Ministry sure to carry their point in Parliament regarding Wilkes; the result in Westminster Hall less certain. Concerning money matters. His interest in Franklin's son, now Governor of New Jersey. Messages from various friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 November 12; A.L.S. 7p.; Jackson, Richard. London
    Greatly concerned to hear of Franklin's misfortune but hopes by this time the cure is perfectly effected. Concerning some business connected with a grant which he is negotiating for Dr. Franklin with the Messrs. Coxe; search for original draught. Parliament meets on Tuesday, Mr. Wiles' business will come up then; House of Commons will probably express resentment at the use he has made of their privilege; session likely to be one of great heat and animosity; fears something relative to America will be done, very much against his opinion. Question of duty on molasses; will oppose all inland duties laid by Parliament on the colonies. Province of Pennsylvania excluded from all share of the money granted by Parliament for the service of 1761; fears this is not the only ill office the General has done the Province. Mr.Penn on his (Jackson's) side in this matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 November 15; D.S. 2p.; Parker, James
    Bond for B#178 18s. given to Benjamin Franklin. Endorsement by the latter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 November 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Brown, Henton. London
    Acknowledging the receipt of several letters and transmitting a statement of their account with Mr. Franklin. Asks him to recommend them to Richard Jackson, Esq., as bankers for the Province of Pennsylvania to which he is agent. Various failures; fall of stocks. Unsettled state of the Ministry. Question relative to Wilkes; majority in the House; duel fought between him and Sam Martin, late of the Treasury; Wilkes wounded in the body, but not fatally; the paper is voted to be burnt by the hands of the common hangman; and 'tis thought the author will be expelled.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1763 December 27; A.L.S. 8p.; Jackson, Richard. London
    Has had only one letter from him in a great while; hopes he is effectually cured; with such news, could make one thousand people happy. Lord Hyde to take Lord Egmont's place, Lord Halifax has now the administration of American affairs; this mutability no proof of an unstable Ministry. Has a good deal of access to Mr. Grenville, who is at the head of it. American affairs in a critical situation. Thinks Maj. Barker at Manila is the gentleman sought after by Franklin; expects him in England in February on March. Difficulty of the work connected with Messrs. Coxe's application; various other claims to the land. His opinion that the mother country is mistress of the trade of its colonies, that she may prohibit foreign trade and may therefore tax; dreads internal taxes. Messages to Mr. Galloway. Mr. Allen's stand on behalf of the Province. Discusses Indian war. Agrees with Franklin about a plethora of money. People's estimate of Col. Bouquet. Encloses list of Acts sent him by the Agent for the Proprietors. Dr. Pringle's reasons for declining any concern in their scheme.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 2p.; Jackson, Richard
    Mr. Coxe's claim; project for a settlement on the Mississippi. Paper currency. (Fragment.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 January 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Greene, Caty.
    Misfortunes of Dr. Franklin's sister. Family affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 January 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Jackson, Richard. Inner Temple
    Has written him by every packet. Maj. Barker's arrival in England, his intention to sail for America in April, then to take possession of and cultivate his estate; has recommended him to certain friends in America. Several American questions coming before Parliament; constantly occupied comhating dangerous errors in American politics; results not commensurate with his efforts. Has long since given up hope of preventing some Parliamentary tax on North America for the maintenance of troops kept there; his aversion to internal taxes. Customs and prohibitions in trade date from the Long Parliament; wishes this to be the rule of England's conduct on this occasion. A bill in embryo for restraining the paper currency of North America within certain limits; will undoubtedly be carried.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 March 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Price, G. Fort Prince George
    Thanking him for the flattering letter he wrote on his behalf to Messrs. Timothy and Limpirc. Describes the situation of Fort Prince George and its means of defense; it has been besieged more than once and almost starved into surrender before succor arrived. Number of Indians in the vicinity; two thousand warriors in the Cherokee Nation who desire peace; also anxious to aid in any movement against the Creeks,who number three or four thousand fighting men. A report that the Creeks have refused to give up the late murderers as demanded by the Governor; more mischief expected from that quarter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 May 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Moffat, Thomas. Newport, R.I
    Acknowledging favor of 9th ult. Highest degree of heat and cold at Newport, curious about the same in Philadelphia. Causes which produce Yellow or bilious fever. His views as to their College. Agitated by imperfect rumors from England about their Charter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 June 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Canton, Jno. London
    Acknowledging favor of March 14th. Mr. Kinnersley's first experiment in electricity truly a beautiful one; what it proves; his second experiment an extraordinary one; has endeavored in vain to make it in England. Mr. Bowdoin's telescope in Mr. Nairne's hands, who is making a pedestal for it. Describes certain experiments he has made, showing the difference in the compressibility of water, in winter and summer. Other members of the Club send their compliments.
    Printed in Works (sparks, VI, 256).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 July 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Mills, John. London
    Acknowledging his favor of March 10 by Mr. Shadwell. Thanks him for presenting to Col. Elliot the first volume of his 'Husbandry'; requests his acceptance of the rest of that work as a mark of esteem for the memory of his father, Dr. Elliot. Delay in getting the remaining volumes. Sends the fourth volume to Franklin. Greatly obliged for list of American book sellers; will make use of it when the fifth and last volume is completed. Various American seeds he is sending to the Society of Agriculture, Arts and Sciences at Rennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 August 8; L. 1p.; -----, -----. Philadelphia
    Interested in reading Dr. Pringle's account of the meteor; efforts he has made to obtain an accurate account of the one which appeared in Philadelphia on the 20th of July, 1764.
    Mutilated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 August 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Becket, T. London
    Acknowledging favor of June 17th; confesses that Franklin's resentment against him is just; reasons for his delay in sending certain promised articles; assures him it will not happen again. Sends him two packets of reviews, magazines and four pamphlets.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 August 10; A.L.S. 2 p.; Bouquet, Col. Henry. Carlisle
    Desertion has reduced his two battalions to about 750 men; cannot spare so many from his small force; is therefore obliged to apply to the Governor and Commissioners for money to recruit the number lost; begs him to use all his influence with the Board to obtain this favor speedily. Situation quiet, neither disturbed by their active enemy, nor assisted by their indolent frontier friends.
    In duplicate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 August 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Bouquet, Henry. Fort Loudoun
    Expressing his gratitude to Franklin and his sincere affection for him. Sorry to hear his sentiments concerning the government have raised him up enemies; wishes the unhappy disputes in the province might be amicably adjusted. Points out certain errors in the Government. Ministry appear averse to Proprietary governments. Board of Trade has just overset the fine superstructure raised by Lord Egmont, upon the expectation of a grant for the Island of St. John; sends his plan which is much approved of in England. Perused with pleasure the papers Mr. Franklin sent him; wishes the plan of a military frontier could be put in execution. Expects no disturbance until the Ohio is crossed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 August 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Bouquet, Henry. Fort Loudoun
    Acknowledging favor of 16th inst. with the welcome account that his request to the Governor had been granted; grateful for Franklin's warm support. Recapitulates various times when Franklin has promoted the service, rendering timely aid to Gen. Shirley, Gen. Braddock, Lord Loudoun and finally to himself in the execution of the present Act.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 262).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 August 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Bouquet, Henry. Fort Loudoun
    Has the mortification to inform him privately that Bradstreet has granted peace at Presqu' Isle to the Delaware and Shawancsc, without visiting on the least satisfaction for their murders and insults; intends taking no notice of this, but will proceed to the Ohio prepared to treat as enemies every villain of those nations, unless contrary orders come from the General.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 September 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Moffat, Thomas. Newport, R.I
    Thanks him for sending Dr. Heberden's method of inoculating the small-pox, which bears every mark of judgment, candor and benevolence; attention shown to this treatise in New England. At the anniversary meeting of their University, mentions various elections made, to show the progress of learning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 October 26; D.S. Cha[rle]s Moore, Clerk. 1p.; The House of Representatives of the Assembly of Pennsylvania
    Appointment of Benjamin Franklin as agent to Great Britain to assist Rich[ar]d Jackson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 October 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. Woodbridge N.J
    Acknowledging favors of 20th and 25th inst. Concerning certain debts he owes to Mr. Strahan and Mr. Franklin; discusses ways and means of paying them off. Business of the post-office. Will send him the law relating to the division line, but doubts if it contains the information he wants. Discusses the Virginia affair; whether to go there himself, in case of Mr. Royle's death, in order to secure the printing business to Mr. Hunter's son; reasons for and against Mr. Holt's going; for himself is resigned either to say or go, according to Mr. Franklin's desire.
    Printed in Proc. Mass. IIisr Soc., 2d Series, XVI, p. 192.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 October 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Lewis. Woodbridge N.J
    Hears from Mr. Parker that he is going to England; begs him to deliver the enclosed letter to his father or Mr. Cummings; has several times written to his family, but never received any answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Smith, John. Burlington
    Expressing pleasure at his appointment as agent of the Province; no one better qualified for the position. Wishes him success and a safe return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Baynton and Wharton. Philadelphia
    Describing two tracts of land; one on the east side of Lake Champlain, the other on the north side of the Bay of Chaleur; advises a speedy petition to the Lordships for the land, as everything is being taken up.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Quincy, Edmund Jr. Boston
    His wife's death together with several avocations has prevented his writing for some time past. Published in Edes and Gills paper last post-day a letter from his brother Huskc to the Committee of Merchants; a reference in this paper was supposed by some to point to Franklin, assures him that it referred to a person residing in London whose treatise on the subject he hopes to send him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Eckerling, Samuel. Philadelphia
    His brethren, Israel and Gabriel Eckerling, were taken by the French and Indians from the Allegheny Mountains in August, 1757, and some time after sent to Rochelle in France where he is informed they died in the hosptial. Asking Franklin to inquire whether this information be true and to let him know.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 Nov. 13-20; A.L. 1p.; Wharton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging favor of 9th inst. Concerning Franklin's "Remarks on the Protest"; W[illiam] A[llen]'s attitude in the matter. Determined to have the 'Remarks' translated into Dutch. Information received from Col. Bouquet, concerning a request for peace from the Shawanese and Delaware Indians.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Howard, Martin Jr. Newport, R.I
    Hearing of his speedy departure for London, embraces this opportunity to write him by a steamer bound thither. Flatters himself that Franklin's zeal will not be exclusively devoted to the correction of abuses in his own Province. Rhode Island but a burlesque on order and government, and not likely to improve unless the Constitution is altered; a petition to the King now in the hands of Jos. Harrison who sailed three weeks back; thinks it may be in Franklin's power to facilitate this matter. Has lost a valuable and affectionate wife.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Introducing Mr. Charles Russel, son of the Hon. James Russel of Charlestown.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Jackson, Richard. London
    Mischief and danger to America and Pennsylvania likely to ensure from the disturbances and dispute in the latter Province. His high opinion of Mr. Allen's honesty and good sense; this and other reasons induced him to open his mind to him more freely than he should, on the subjects of Pennsylvania's privileges, the proprietary Government, the power of the Crown, etc.; had no idea that Mr. Allen would make these sentiments public; intended chiefly for Franklin's ear. Has just heard of the event of the election; not sorry for Franklin, but only for the Province; looks upon all hopes of reconciliation as vanished. Messages to the Governor of New Jersey.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 272).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1764 November 23; A.L. 4p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Wrote him from New Castle the substance of the Address of the Lower Counties' Assembly, in which they inform the Crown that, although they are governed under the same charter as the people of Pennsylvania, their laws are different; proves this to be wrong, as well as certain other facts of theirs. Proprietary party still
    industriously endeavoring to prevent their design to change the government; petitions to this effect, from the Corporation of the City and also from the presbyterians, to go over with Mr. Hamilton. Debility of the Proprietary Government; instances the case of a Dutchman appointed sheriff at Lancaster and the refusal of the Irish Presbyterians to serve under him, ending with his forced flight to save his life; no measures taken to bring the offenders to justice. Hostile attitude of the Governor towards all, supporting the measures in favor of the Crown.
    [Conclusion missing.]
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 276).